this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at sc-radio.net
SE radio is brought to you by the IEEE
computer Society software Magazine
online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm your host Jeff Doolittle I'm excited
to invite Luca galante as our guest on
the show today for a discussion about
platform engineering
Luca leads product at Humana Tech
providing the platform orchestrator that
lets engineering teams remove
bottlenecks by enabling them to build
code-based golden paths for developers
he is a core contributor of the platform
engineering community he hosts platform
con the number one platform engineering
conference and writes at platform weekly
which goes out to 10 000 readers every
week Luca routinely speaks to tens of
engineering teams every month he
summarizes his learnings and takeaways
from looking at hundreds of devops
setups into crisp insightful reads for
everyone in the industry from beginner
Ops to Cloud experts Luca welcome to the
show
hey Jeff thanks for having me let's Dive
Right In what is platform engineering
yeah so platform Engineering in my view
is the art because it's really an art
more than a science of basically taking
all the tech and tools that you have
floating around in the Enterprise today
and binding them into a simple golden
path that removes cognitive load on the
individual contributor and a developer
and enables cell service for engineers
using it and the superset of these
golden hats is what is often referred to
as an internal developer platform or IDP
for short which is effectively the end
product of the platform engineer team or
platform engineering organization so
let's unpack those a little bit when you
say cognitive load I'm imagining we're
just trying to make it easier for people
to think through complex problems and
the way you're describing that there's a
couple Concepts there that maybe we can
dig into a little bit more you mentioned
self-service uh be probably good
addicting to that a little bit and then
let's talk a little bit more about what
exactly is a golden path and how does
that relate to this idea of self-service
yeah so cognitive load is basically
referring to the fact that
if you look back 10 15 years ago and I
just wanted to do a simple you know
deploy to test something in a preview
environment you know that was as
developer I would have to probably touch
like maybe a script one or two tools
deployment tools and that was about it
the reality today is a lot more complex
at that you have all this you know Cloud
native sort of like Technologies and
trends that overlap with each other
which makes it quite overwhelming to do
simple operations like that and so
developers are often you know almost
scared of you know going touch does like
three four different scripts that Helm
chart those terraform modules over there
and so and so forth because you know
there's scared of screwing things up and
so that's what we mean by cognitive load
and so the job of the platform
engineering team in in that context is
basically to listen to developers figure
out what their issues are and then
design a golden path that let them lets
them consume these different tools and
scripts and you know underlying
infrastructure and technologies that
they need to do their job in a way that
is
easy but specifically that gives them
the right level of context and the right
level of obstruction that they choose
right so that's where it's really really
important that the platform team has a
very tight feedback loop with developers
because you're going to have different
types of developers different types of
users with different preferences and we
can get into that later but that's
really how you craft those different
golden paths and ultimately that's also
what makes an IDP internal developer
platform different from a pass that you
know is a lot less customizable and a
lot less flexible for different types of
users
let me say pass I I believe you're
talking about platform as a service
which essentially is basically just a
lot of tools and Technologies and you
have to understand them all in order to
put them together and it sounds like
what these golden paths do is they
provide maybe more cohesive and clear
ways to adopt some of those Technologies
and services without maybe needing as
much detailed understanding about all
the complexity about all those Services
is that a good way of looking at it no
okay so passes is kind of the opposite
of that right so like pass is actually
like an oversimplification like an
extreme abstraction and it's usually you
know I mean the OG pass that most people
might be familiar with is a Roku right
now it is there are a lot many more that
popped up that are a lot more
specialized in different use cases but
you know the idea of a pass is basically
you know you have the product team
behind a pass offering that says hey
I've you know figured out the market and
I've worked out that this level of
obstruction is the right minimum common
denominator across all these different
engineer organizations and so off you go
here you can use this and you know I
often tell teams if you are you know 50
developers minus right if you're like 20
30 engineers and not everybody is an
expert in Helm charts and so on and so
forth you know ISC and so on then
go use a pass right like a pass is
actually what you want to use because
it's it's much easier it can get you up
and running without everybody needing to
understand everything the issue with
passes are you know they they don't
really scale and the Enterprise size and
so when you cross that kind of you know
80 to 100 Engineers mark That's when
usually you need to start crafting those
different golden paths that we've been
talking about for different users and
this will happen at the same time that
your you know Cloud footprint and stack
gets more complex and so that's where
you basically want to make sure that
you're transitioning from a simplified
pass offering that doesn't let you
customize because again the product team
of that pass says hey I figured out the
minimum denominator but obviously that
means you kind of actually tweak it as
much and so then that's where you move
to a platform engineering basically
model where you have an internal
platform team that takes the different
tools of platform engineering that can
be both open source tools and Commercial
offerings and then ties them into this
past like experience but that will be
really you know geared towards the
different types of users across the
different types of teams I think I
understand now and I think the Heroku
analogy is really helpful so let me take
another stab at summarizing that and
maybe I'll get it right this time with
something like Heroku as an example
that's a platform as a service which in
a sense that's that is a form of
platform engineering it sounds like
you're saying here we've made some
decisions for you but the challenge is
you're saying that doesn't scale once
your team gets Beyond a certain size
because the design decisions that went
into something like that platform as a
service are very constrained they're
specific maybe to certain team size
certain use cases maybe they don't work
at Enterprise scale you know and and
massive you know global scale and at
that point you need to start crafting
your own platform as a service
but there may not be a one-size-fits-all
for your entire organization and so you
need to create multiple golden passes
you're describing it so the teams can be
successful instead of trying to create
the single platform as a service to rule
them all did it get it right this time
you did and that's what we call an
intern developer platform right and
that's to me is like really the key
difference because sometimes people are
like oh it's just like a pass I'm like
well it's a past like experience but on
top of Enterprise Tech and tools right
and that's really the key difference
I see so why the two terms platform
engineering and internal developer
platform how do those terms kind of
relate and how are they how are they
different yeah so platform engineering
is really sort of like the discipline
that for me stems from devops the
original promise of devops which is you
build it you run it right which became
basically impossible to actualize in a
world where you know you have 10 000
cncf tools landscape and everything that
we already talked about right where like
developers are really overwhelmed which
then turns into a ticket ops issue and
then operations are under pressure and
there's just a lot of friction in the
system and so this like great idea of
devops originally of taking down the
barriers between developers and
operations really actually becomes a
pretty frustrating reality in the vast
majority of cases and so the solution to
that really is platform engineering
right and so platform engineering is in
that context in evolution of devops that
actually enables true devops enables
true you build it around it at the
Enterprise scale because again you know
if you go back to the past example at
that scale you basically have two
options let's say you're 20 Engineers
right like either not everybody's a pro
in your infrastructure stack and then
you want to go the pathway or everybody
is a pro and then you can actually do
true devops right you can actually have
everybody do everything the problem is
that doesn't scale right it doesn't
scale as your setup gets more complex
and especially as you're adding more
people
and so platform engineering is you know
enabling true devops in the Enterprise
and the end product of the platform
engineer org is an internal developer
platform okay can you give some specific
examples of maybe in your experience or
teams you've seen what are some specific
struggles that they face when they're
trying to have as you say if no one's a
pro and you just pick a simple thing and
you go with it or everyone's a pro and
then reality is usually far more mixed
right so I imagine you have situations
where maybe you have one or two really
seasoned people and then a bunch of
people who aren't and how does that kind
of play out in in struggle so that our
listeners can maybe you know feel this
pain themselves and say ah yes I've
experienced that I've seen that myself
yeah 100 I mean you know one of the most
basic examples that we see a lot is
especially you know fairly large
Enterprise
are developers requesting a new
environment or a new piece of
infrastructure like a database right and
that can literally take up to two weeks
sometimes right and so the velocity and
productivity of the of the development
team drops significantly and obviously
they're frustrated right because they're
just like hey man I just want a preview
environment to test something like how
is this so complicated right and on the
flip side of that is the operations team
who's getting all this like inbound
tickets right and that's what we call
them ticket ops right and they're
completely underwater because instead of
working on fun problems and figuring out
how to load balance that production over
here and all these clusters and just
like or you know adding new sorts of
infrastructure because developers are
requesting it no instead they're really
bogged down in you know constantly
putting out fires and really cope do
copy paste work right like if you talk
to a lot of this like devops and even
just like you know platform teams that
are they're doing the wrong type of
offer engineering they're basically just
like you know copy pacing the same stuff
over and over again and you know they're
very well paid for it usually but it's
just like very you know non-fulfilling
work and what ultimately suffers is the
overall not just you know organizations
in terms of like time to Market gets
really affected by this but you know
also your you know the overall
satisfaction you know in police
satisfaction and just like you know
simply put happiness of the people
working in this setup is decreasing and
so if you think about you know how cell
service helps in that case right and you
know by the way the first sort of like
companies right they've figured out okay
this thing is a problem right where the
very kind of large tech companies
leading engineering organizations right
that were the ones that had the most
complex setups right that were getting
increasingly complex and we're also the
ones onboarding literally hundreds of
Developers a month right and so they
quickly saw hey this idea of devops
doesn't scale like there is no way that
I expect all these new people that I'm
hiring to quickly onboard and be a pro
at this increasingly complex Cloud
native stack kubernetes is Kafka
terraform Helm charts all this stuff
that keeps getting more complex right
okay so hundreds of people onboarding no
way they're going to understand
everything about everything something's
got to change okay exactly and they said
hmm we need to build some sort of
platform layer here in between the
operation side of things and the
development side of things so the
developer can still serve and so the
whole idea is you know the whole true
you build that you run it is enable
developers to configure their workloads
their applications on their own have
their workloads consume the right type
of infrastructure the right type of
environment postgres database the right
type of you know how Helm charts and
terraform files under the hood right but
removing that complexity away from them
right so that they can simply declare
for instance hey I need my workload to
have a DNS and a postgres database and a
whatever and then the platform goes and
resolves all of those things
automatically right and then deploys the
application for instance in a new Fresh
preview environment right and in all of
this they didn't have to slack or talk
to an operations colleague and
operations can you know do their job and
do more interesting things with their
time so let's dig into that a little bit
and I imagine there's maturity levels as
far as platform engineering goes but
let's go all to the end state of when
we're in the perfect platform
engineering world that we all want to be
in at some point in the future which
hopefully sooner rather than later but I
imagine it takes time to get there how
does the self-service play about like
what's the delivery mechanism by which
the developers find the appropriate
documentation the appropriate you know
redelivering documentation via websites
are we giving them portals are we giving
them clis or other things you know talk
a little bit about the landscape of if
I'm a developer in a platform
engineering environment what is my
day-to-day kind of look like with how
I'm operating with this platform
engineering internal developer platform
that is a great question and I think
probably worth answering with one of the
anti-partners that I see a lot of kind
of platform teams falling into which is
kind of like hey you know I am technical
management and I'm speaking with my
platform team I'm like hey guys we need
to improve developer experience right
and it's like this like very top-down
thing we're going to build a platform
we're going to improve developer
experience and so on right and that's
kind of like where you're asking like
what's the developer experience look
like right and then the mistake did a
lot of platform image initiatives make
is they basically look at developer
experience from a chronological
perspective right so they go like okay
what do developers do first they create
a service then they you know add some
features whatever deployed to dev then
test the staging production and so on
right and so they look at this
chronologically and then they stop at
the first step which is service creation
right and then they decide to you know
look at something that's like very
trendy in the market like a backstage
for instance and build a portal right
and the problem with that is that you
know how much time are you actually
investing in service creation right I
mean if you are a you know crazy high
performing you know streaming company
like Spotify probably quite a bit and
you know you have like thousands of
developers on this and so on and so that
makes a lot of sense and you know for
some other companies in mind as well but
in the vast majority of cases it's you
know less than one percent of the times
you're actually and on on service
creation and so actually all that work
that you're doing in building that
portal is providing you with a
relatively pretty low Roi right and you
know from the perspective the developer
now you just gave me like a UI to click
around once every you know X weeks
really and that's pretty much it right
so
and that can feel good from a platform
initiative perspective because it feels
like you you know you've built this
platform layer you know now technical
management has a dashboard to look at
likely which they always love but really
you haven't fixed the most pain of the
developer right and so how do you how do
you avoid that and by the way I just
want to make sure that I get this across
like I'm not you know disregarding stuff
like backstage we've worked at Humanity
very closely with the backstage product
team it's a great product I think but
you know it's a great product for a very
precise set of customers and a lot of
times we see you know because Spotify or
because Google has done it then
everybody wants to do it and a lot of
time is not the same thing right you're
not Spotify you're not Google for at
least for most of our listeners right
exactly exactly you don't have the same
level of resources the same Talent right
yada yada yada sorry you're just not
Google and so some of the things they do
could be great kubernetes is a great
example right but not all of them right
so really I think in that sense be wary
of Consultants you know that come in and
tell you hey yeah we really need to
think about how we get you to you know
how you get your platform initiative to
be like you know airbnbs and it's like
not really so anyways but go back to
your question so
you know that's an example of for
instance a UI UI heavy interface and
that can be a path in our experience and
what I've seen a lot in the market is
not the best path because a lot of
people will feel obstructed away you
know by using a Eli right and so this
like click Ops setting a lot of the
times you know especially from the more
senior backing Engineers you're going to
get huge pushback they're really not
going to like it and so that's where you
know kind of what we were talking about
earlier becomes really really important
which is as the platform team you really
need to figure out what's the right
level of obstruction what's the golden
path what's the right interface and
interaction method for your developers
and you might have you know a simple UI
for some use case and from some teams
but what we see in the majority of cases
is code base is what works best right
because it naturally
fits into the workflow that developers
are used to how they're normally used to
like design things configure things and
you know provision things and so that's
where we see the you know High
performing platform teams and some of
the most successful platform initiatives
they usually are driven by a code-based
interface so how is that delivered
exactly then are we saying let's say I'm
in Java my developers are in Java it's
the platform team delivering them just
are they looking at the GitHub
repository that's shared or are they
getting Maven packages that they're
grabbing and been you know loading the
jar files in or you know how is this
kind of again trying to get back to that
if I'm the developer day-to-day
experience who's leveraging this
platform engineering internal
development platform how am I in that
context interacting with it and being
successful using it well I mean not to
kind of speak my own game too much but
one of the standards that we've open
sourced and that has grown a lot in the
market in the last
three to six months has been score and
score is a workload specification that
precisely lets you do that right lets
you basically use a yaml file right such
as a yaml file that lets you specify
what your workload needs to run and you
need to do it once and then it's going
to resolve itself depending on the
environment that you're running on that
you're deploying to and the dependencies
that you specify in the workload it's
going to resolve all that environment
specific right every time you deploy and
so from the perspective the developer
you specify in an environment agnostic
way what your workload needs to run and
then score plus a platform orchestrator
like human tech for instance does
everything else right and and so in this
case it's a simple yaml file it can also
be you know you mentioned a CLI it can
also you know it can also just be like a
CLI but in this case to keep it like
fully code based it'd be literally just
like a score yaml file that lives in
your repo so for some of our listeners
who may still be in more of a client
server environment which you know let's
be honest it may be the 21st century and
we may almost be a quarter of the way
through it but there are still a lot of
companies that are working to try to
move from more of a client server model
into more of a cloud native model so
explore a little bit more of what you
mean when you say a workload just to
make sure that for listeners who are
maybe less familiar with things like
kubernetes and Cloud orchestration
platforms that they kind of have a sense
of what we're talking about
absolutely so a workload you know in our
world is really a representation of an
application effectively right and
specifically of a containerized
application right and that's really you
know when we talk Cloud native we're
usually token containers and that's the
vast majority of you know what we see in
terms of like you know platform being
platforms being built because again like
if you think about you know platform
engineering as we said is this like you
know enabling true you build it you run
it is you know really devops for the
cloud native era right so that's kind of
like what we're talking about here and
so in this context a workload really is
you know a unit where you specify you
know that connects basically to external
dependencies this could be something
like a DNS it could connect to a
database it could connect to like a
Secrets manager an external Secrets
manager like a vault instance by
hashicorp stuff like that right and so
that's really the the unit that you know
in the vast majority of cases developers
are going to be concerned with right and
so when you're designing your platform
you really want to optimize for this
specific use case and for this specific
unit right and like what is the you know
what is the best way to let developers
just describe their ideal application
architecture right through this workload
you know specification which is you know
ultimately what for instance core is
it's a workload specification so we've
explored a little bit about these
Concepts where you you could build a
developer portal like we've said you
could do that but maybe this place is
where the ROI is not there we've talked
a little bit about declarative tooling
and clis is there anything else from a
developer's day-to-day experience where
you know they're going to benefit more
from a platform engineering approach
like are there other things like maybe
you know you talk about containerization
maybe there's things like sdks or other
things I just want to give a listener is
a flavor of you know if I
work in a company that's doing platform
engineering you know how is what are
other ways this is benefiting me as a
developer totally I mean look I think
the main thing here is you know in a in
a working a company that is using cloud
and Technologies you already benefit
from everything that is like clouding
Technologies provide out of the box and
we don't need to cover all of that but
the key thing with the company that is
using is applying good platform
engineering practices is you'll get the
benefits of using the cloud native
Technologies without the downsides which
can really be a bummer in a lot of cases
and honestly like the easiest way of
explaining it is they translate into
waiting times like right from the
developer perspective I think the
biggest pain is literally waiting like
you just want to get something started
you want to do a quick experiment you
want to test something you want to you
just want to get a simple database or a
simple environment and you can't get
that right and and that's really painful
and so you basically go from like
waiting let's say an hour two hours
three days two weeks in the worst case
I've seen right to like zero it's
instant it's like you click about them
you run a command you deploy script and
whatever it is that you need it just is
self-served it just happens right and I
mean the other pain point and some
people in the audience might relate to
is what I call Shadow operations right
and this is a little bit kind of like
what you were touching on which is you
know you have the the interesting
scenario sometimes where you have Junior
developers and Senior developers in
product teams right and you have
operations that's completely underwater
as we described and then you have and so
basically what ends up you know
naturally emerging is
that the senior colleagues will
basically start taking over Ops right
because like the junior colleagues would
be like hey can you help me with this
can you help with that and they're
they're ones that are more familiar with
like you know handling the scripts and
all these things and so they'll end up
doing it which then basically makes them
in a further bottleneck right so now you
have like operations being a modern like
on an organizational level then you have
the senior people being a bottleneck on
a team level and frankly you have you
know your most experienced and frankly
most expensive right like development
resources being blocked and blocking
adders which basically just like
compounds this frustration right and so
you can think of like what's in it for
you as a developer frustration
disappears waiting times disappear and
so you get all the benefit of cloud
native without a non-size yeah that
focus on bottlenecks I think is really
interesting and I'll put a link in the
show notes to listeners to a book called
the goal by Eli Gold rat and there's a
similar book that a lot of us are
familiar with called The Phoenix project
but it's essentially a redo of the goal
for software engineering but the concept
of bottlenecks I think is really
important and you know I've seen it a
million times where you have a team with
one senior engineer and they throw five
Juniors on the team and they think
that's going to work and the problem is
the senior engineer is no longer a
senior engineer they're basically just
constantly interrupted so the the
juniors are waiting on the senior to do
things but the seniors constantly
interrupted by the junior so they can't
do things and there you have it yeah
I call it Shadow Ops but yeah precisely
that yeah and I guess in this case
shadow in a bad way you know not like
you know it's cool I mean the shadows
and I'm Incognito it's like no this is
like bad this is like you know someone's
lurking in the alley and they're gonna
like take you out kind of Shadow like
this is no good exactly exactly yeah so
let's switch gears and let's look at the
other side so we've kind of looked at
you know if I'm a developer and I'm
working with platform engineering kind
of what is this going to give me and
we've talked about some of the the
things you might do to deliver that and
how it can help with reducing
bottlenecks because there's consistent
practices there's declarative models
there's ability to basically spin up the
infrastructure I need and the platform
tooling that I need much more quickly
instead of all the waiting around in the
bottlenecks but on the other side of
things so now let's say I'm somebody
who's building an internal developer
platform what does my day-to-day look
like what are the kinds of things that
I'm doing to build out this developer
experience within our organization yeah
it's a great question so I think the
main thing that you're doing is
listening right I think if you were to
kind of like cluster the two sort of
like key skill sets for a good platform
engineer in my opinion are you know
product mindset
and communication basically right and so
let's break that down so proud mindset
you know is something that we really
advocate for a lot in the community and
it's the whole idea of platform as a
product right and it's the idea that
like hey if you come from a devil's
background you know we were talking
about it earlier before we got on which
is the usual sort of mindset there is
I'll build all these systems and I'll
teach it to the developers right instead
you know you don't want to do that
because again as you scale and as you're
adding more systems that's just not you
know sustainable and so what you want to
do instead is enable them to self-serve
whatever it is that they need without
having to understand now if they want to
learn if they want to understand it you
know you have different sort of like
knobs that you can that you can serve
turn and and kind of like lower the
abstraction and give them more context
right or you can do the the other way
around basically and so a lot of the
work really becomes figuring out what's
the right level of obstruction what's
the right type of golden path for the
right type of users and so let's get
more sort of pragmatic let's say you are
working with a you know a senior backing
engineer right and they really love
working with their yaml files into ham
charge now if you're going to provide
them with a golden path that is
basically a very abstracted like UI
where they can only do a couple of
clicks and they can no longer specify
what's the amount of CPU that my pods is
consuming or like all these things
they're going to be really mad at you
and the you know likelihood of your
platform engineering initiative you know
working out is getting lower and lower
similarly though if you are building a
you know an interface and a golden path
for your let's say junior front-end
engineer who basically just want to
deploy their application their front end
somewhere to test some changes that
they've made on the code they don't care
whether you're writing on eks or gke
they probably don't care whether you're
running with kubernetes at all and you
know you could argue they shouldn't and
so you know in that case given them
access to how charts May makes
absolutely no sense right and so then
you might want to give them like whether
it's UI or as I said still even in that
case I think code base interactions are
preferred by all types of developers
regardless of seniority and so then you
might want to do that right and so then
your day-to-day as a platform engineer
really becomes that you know at least
for one part really like listening to
developers and like building this
feedback loop and figuring out what is
the right level of obstruction in
context that I need to provide to them
on the flip side of that is then
communication right and you know I often
say hey if you were to plot on a graph
where like the the y-axis is
communication skills and the x-axis is
time right and you'd start all the way
to your you know from kind of like your
sys admin to your infrastructure devops
Cloud Ops you know and then eventually
platform engineer right it would
basically be a curve up into the right
and the reason is you know progressively
these roles have had to like be better
and better communicator and the Pinnacle
at the moment of that is the platform
engineering why because you need to be a
really effective Communicator with three
different group of stakeholders your
developers and we already covered that
right like figuring out the right level
obstruction sell it to them make sure
that everybody's happy make sure that
your you know your senior back-end
people understand that you're not taking
context away from them that you're
avoiding them doing Shadow Ops
eventually and so on so forth right so
that's how you speak to developer but
the the lingo that you use to speak to
your sea level which is another
stakeholder is completely different
right if you talk about like developer
experience look it's funny because a lot
of times you know ctOS will tell you oh
we really care about developer
experience and their reality is like a
lot of times they actually don't like
what they care about is you know time to
Market is your Dora Matrix and yada yada
right and so that's how you need to sell
it to them right it's a completely
different language that you need to
speak really and then the third group is
operations and I think this is something
that a lot of people get wrong which is
they sort of you know don't make very
clear from the get-go that the mission
and vision of the platform team is that
of shipping a product right so we're
connecting to the first point we said
and not basically ending up as yet
another you know Ops devops Team right
and that needs to be made really clear
to the developers right because you
don't want them to just like send ticket
requests but physically but especially
to other existing operation scene
because again it's not like the platform
team is replacing the current you know
SRE you still need an SRE you might need
in fact even like multiple SRE and
infrastructure teams and even multiple
platform teams you know that's something
that we see in very large organizations
where they compete to each other but
that's a separate thing and so you need
to speak to them and make sure hey there
is a clear separation of concerns here
you're the one like you know worrying
about maintainability scalability
reliability I'm the one worrying about
building a product which makes your job
better and easier right and so you need
to it's really complex multi-stakeholder
conversations that you constantly need
to juggle with and so that's really what
your day-to-day looks like and this is
why by the way the kind of like role of
the platform product manager I think
becomes super crucial right because
they're really going to be the link
basically between
old as different stakeholders the
platform team right and there there
really need to be the kind of top
Communicator in in that case Yeah you
mentioned listening is an important
factor in good communication it's it's
like the old school wisdom that you have
two ears and one mouth because you
should listen twice as much as you speak
of course here on a podcast which is all
about us talking and our our listeners
listening but what I appreciate about
that too is you know we've we've heard
of all these different forms of
something driven development there's
Behavior driven development there's
domain driven development there's all
these different things but what some of
us I've heard joke about in the industry
is something called pain driven
development
but essentially pain driven development
goes back in some ways to that
conversation we had before about Roi and
if you can find where the maximum pain
is with the you know relatively low
efforts to resolve the pain then you're
going to have good Roi whereas if you
take something that's not that painful
but you put a bunch of time and effort
into it then effectively you've just
you've reduced pain but you haven't gone
for the big guns I think that's a lot of
what we're talking about here is where's
the pain where you wait you mentioned
waiting that's pain we mentioned
bottlenecks that's pain so how do we
it's like a pain reduction strategy for
our engineering teams a hundred percent
I love that Framing and that is exactly
how we think about it at humanitek we've
actually surveyed a bunch of like 2000
or so engineering teams of all different
sizes and what we asked them was you
know basically we were trying to think
like okay how do you identify the pain
right and so we asked them okay out of a
hundred deployments how often do you do
this things like how often do you create
new service how often do you spin up a
new environment how often do you
provision database how often do you do a
rollback how often do you change you
know conflicts whatever all these things
right and then we and then we ask them
to basically attach a time to that right
like so how long it takes on the
development side of things and how long
it takes on the upside of things and so
with that Matrix in front of you it's
really easy like that's like you'll
really find the pains yeah you know
screaming at you it's like oh it's
clearly here here and here and usually
it's in configuration management right
like in handling application
configurations infrastructure
configurations right like dealing with
those Helm charts dealing with those
yaml files dealing with those you know
terraforming IC modules that's where we
see it oftentimes like there is the
highest amount of fear cognitive load
and pain in the system absolutely but
what's interesting about that to me too
is every organization is going to have
different amount of pain and different
kinds of pain and so I think what this
speaks to too is I've seen and talked to
platform teams where it sometimes feels
like they're trying to create the next
one platform to rule them all and what
we're talking about here there's aspects
of this really of servant leadership
where if you're a platform engineer your
job is not to come up with the coolest
platform to rule them all and spend all
your time you know in the cloud working
with the tools and of course you have to
do that to understand them but the
reason you're understanding them is so
that you can make developers lives
easier and the only way you can do that
is by actually understanding what
they're struggling with you can't just
in a vacuum say here's the new cool
platform it's but does it really solve
their problems and I think that hearkens
back to what you say is the product
focus when it's a product the customer
is the one who's driving the Innovation
and driving the areas of pain that need
to be reduced not the person who's
building the implementation or building
out the infrastructure 100 and that's
the thing the focus needs to be on
making something that is 10x better for
the developer not for yourself not for
you to play with like shining new
technologies and like oh I built this
thing using that it really needs to be
better for developers because otherwise
there's also not enough incentive for
them to move over from the current
status quo and setup over to the
platform right and frankly you know when
we're talking about the problems that we
talked about like you know if you're
waiting a week and now you're waiting
zero it's at least 10x better so it's
not like you know because a lot of times
like oh build a 10x better thing it's
like it's hard right like hoarders of
magnitudes are hard but I think if you
understand the starting point which is
usually pretty bad it's actually not
impossible to achieve but you need to
deliver that right if you're delivering
something that's like meh better like
it's just not going to cut it right and
then sometimes you know it's like the
most obvious thing to say but still I
think you know sometimes people just
don't they're like roll out this
platform and they you know they just
like Boop you know drop it on top of the
existing setup and then they expect
people to use it you know and there's no
like Lighthouse approach and no rollout
strategy you know and sometimes even
worse they force developers to use it
you know so those are all anti-patterns
that we don't see too much of to be
honest but it don't fall back to this
idea of like platform as a product you
know and the Beautiful Thing by the way
about treating your Prof from as a
product is that all the learnings and
best practice stuff that we've had for
the last like 30 40 Years of product
management apply so like all this like
rollout strategies and it's like you
know find a lighthouse team and then
progressively increase users from there
like measure things get feedback
qualitative quantitative blah blah like
all the things that we already know of
from building out our products just
apply to build your platform and so the
moment and this is why it's super
important I think and sometimes here I
do see like a lot of people fail which
is like they just take a bunch of devops
Engineers that have like a different
type of mindset you know which is just
like building infrastructure not
shipping products really and you know
and it's like hey now you're our
platform team go build a platform and
then guess what like they don't make
that transition right because they don't
have the right PM they don't have the
right
framework around them to succeed and
that's how sometimes platform niches
fail yeah yeah I think this has been a
development in the industry over the
last you know few decades in particular
where it feels like in the early stages
and it kind of made sense of the day
which is it was very much technology
focused and we've all seen the jokes and
the tropes and the memes about the
software Engineers who only care about
tech and they have absolutely zero human
skills at all and a lot of us have grown
very weary of that and I've really tried
to spend a lot of time encouraging
software Engineers to hone their soft
skills and their human skills because a
lot of what we're talking about here is
look you have to understand the
technology someone has to and if you're
gonna lower the barrier to adoption to a
developer it behooves you to understand
the technology but then you have to hone
your soft skills and your human skills
so that you can actually help other
people be more productive and to me
senior engineer ideally is less about
your technological prowess as critical
as that is
but it's also about your ability to
understand the needs of others and make
them successful to me that's a true 10x
engineer by the way is not somebody
who's 10 times faster than everybody
else it's somebody who makes everybody
else around them more successful Yeah a
hundred percent and you know
still you see so many people thinking
that oh my God my platform initiative is
going to fail because I picked the wrong
Tech
it's almost never the case right it's
like it's not because you picked Argo
over Flex that you're gonna fail it's
because you failed at the cultural
transformation right that's why org
Transformations fail they fail because
of culture and objects of Technology
yeah the problem is people the solution
is people and that's the problem right
exactly but also the opportunity and I
think there's the call out to our
listeners
so let's switch gears a little bit here
and talk about standards because as
we're talking about I'm thinking of this
idea in my mind and when I say that let
me frame it a little bit there's so many
knobs there's so many options there's so
many things you could do and I imagine
there's some risk here that if you're
trying to do Platform engineering that
you can over abstract we've talked about
that on the one side of things like you
just say you know everybody gets Heroku
and that's it like that and not to pick
on Heroku that's great for certain
workflows and use cases but it doesn't
work for everybody and on the other side
of things though I imagine there's under
abstraction and I imagine you're going
to start there no matter you know how
hard you try you're never gonna get the
perfect abstraction right the first time
so maybe talk a little bit about in your
experience if there's ways that teams
can kind of figure out how do we do that
how do we kind of manage the change
management of the dynamism of this over
time so we don't have permanent over
abstractions or permanent under
abstractions of these you know platform
concerns
yeah it's a great question and you know
just last week I was giving you a
presentation at platform days Sao Paulo
this is the first event that the
community did there and I was actually
talking about the 10 fallacies apart
from engineering and you know it's funny
you mentioned that because like two of
the core ones are what I call the
abstraction fallacy and then the freedom
fallacy right and abstraction fast is
basically like think about a developer
just staring at a wall you know and
they're like I can't do anything anymore
right now right and so there really as
we said you want to build golden path
not golden cages right and abstractions
are really good but they're also good if
you want to use them and if there is
kind of like a side path that you know
where you can circumvent them if you
need to right so to be specific let's
say you know your IDP spins up a default
terraform module if a developer requests
the database right and this has been
vetted by security it worked Works in
all cases right most of the cases but
then one day comes and one of your
developers has an eligible Edge case
right so what you want your platform to
be able to do is that it lets the
developer extend that terraform module
on their own you know according to
permissions and roles and permissions
and so on to respond to the edge case
now if the edge case happens more and
more then you realize hey this is a new
golden path right and so then you take
it and you formalize it and your
standardize it right and this is how
actually the platform becomes like a
listening Channel almost right to
basically capture information from the
developers to the platform Engineers
right we've all seen that picture of you
know the college campus right where you
have the regular like Pathways and then
like all the ones in the middle on the
fields and so you know the platform in
that sense becomes a really good way of
like seeing those things form and then
format analyzing them before they sort
of formalize themselves on their own
because it's sort of like a truism apart
from engineer is if you don't build your
platform it will build itself right the
problem is it will build itself in the
wrong ways right and then so the
opposite of that is a freedom fallacy
right and the freedom fallacy is you
know where you basically have your
platform team going like AWS console
access for everybody you know yeah and
and it's like hey oh hell you want to
use help great you want to use Argo
terraform you want to know kubernetes
pluses boom right and so then you get
all the downsides of scale with no
benefits you get Shadow Ops for activity
drops all the right that we talked about
and so again the solution is like think
really really hard where additional
cognitive load is really necessary it
might be in some cases right but you
know Aaron Erickson this guy that cork
contributor as well the platform
engineering community friend and he
built well ended up becoming the adopted
platform initiative at Salesforce he
said you know to run a thousand
different services in kubernetes you
shouldn't need a thousand kubernetes
experts right and so that I think
encapsulates this like Freedom fallacy
really well right so you really want to
always optimize for the degree of
cognitive load that the team is able to
handle and is willing to handle not more
than that it doesn't need to right so
those are like kind of like the two
sides of the same coin yeah an analogy
that comes to my mind is is one I use a
lot which is if you're going to build a
house you could do everything yourself
power generation Water Sanitation water
Discovery you could do a well like you
do everything yourself and then you
could say that anyone who's going to
work on this house needs to know
everything about all of that kind of
stuff but at some point we've discovered
that that's not very robust it doesn't
really scale very well it doesn't
standardize it's not repeatable but you
know that's how people used to build
houses right power generation was a
water wheel right I mean these kinds of
things and now what you say is you're
still an expert on how to build the
house we're not saying you're not smart
but what we're saying is you don't need
to be a mechanical engineer an
electrical engineer a chemical engineer
a civil engineer you can focus on
building a house and platform
engineering is going to provide all of
those services that you need to generate
and distribute and all this kind of
stuff so then you could be expert on the
specific domain of how do I build a
house and you don't have to be an expert
on the domain of everything else that
gives you the service delivery that you
need in order to build that house
a hundred percent yeah great so are
there any traditional best practices
that we haven't covered yet that fit
well with platform engineering you know
what are things we want to keep from
what we've learned from devops or from
what we've learned in the past that we
can still continue to leverage just to
give our listeners a sense of oh these
are good things I'm already doing I'm
already familiar with let's keep doing
those things in this platform
engineering world
yeah I mean I think this really
reconnects to what we were saying
earlier which is the beauty of treating
your platform as a product is the older
product best practices that with
learning product management in the last
few decades apply and so I think we've
covered a few of them I think another
interesting one that I've seen as well
and so like starting from kind of like
what's the issue like it's another one
of the fallacies which is the sort of
like the loudest voice fallacy and it's
like really funny one because it's like
think about your hardcore backend
engineer Arduino lover
asked their partner to get married
through prompt commands right so that
person we know who that person is in our
team and they're usually the loudest
voice in your team and they're also very
articulate and they are going to be the
ones that a lot of times are gonna be
like oh hey you know oh this platform is
abstracting to me or like this doesn't
work for me blah blah blah right and so
here's a really important thing that I
think we've all learned from the last
few Decades of shipping products which
is a good product and in this case like
a good platform is not designed for the
strongest Link in the chain but for the
weakest one right and so when you are
designing that make sure that you ask
obviously like a diverse group of people
individually though right because if
you're gonna put like a hardcore SRE in
a room right with a couple of Junior
JavaScript developers you probably get
the wrong input because especially like
you know I again I was speaking about
this in Brazil last week and you have
certain cultures where this is even more
true than others right so a culture like
Brazil is usually you know quite
sensitive to like the seniority more
than others and so that's where you'll
see like basically everyone that is like
a little bit more junior or something
like completely be shut down and shut
off by the loudest voice in the room and
that can be quite dangerous and you know
during this process of you figuring out
what to write golden puff and so on for
my organs so that's just another example
I think of again everything that we can
leverage from product management best
practices and is by the way why you know
the product management channel in the
platform engineering slackspace is I
think one of the most interesting ones
right it was actually the one that was
really like started by community members
and it's one of the most fascinating one
for me to look at because you know
really encapsulates if you look at all
the different threads the complexity of
you know all these different challenges
that we talked about and it's really
fascinating it's really interesting so
yeah I think if people are curious about
how old is like product management and
everything that you know what can we
apply for what we already know to
building a platform I think looking
through the lens of product management
is a great way of thinking about it and
probably speaking to a lot of this
triggers for me I thought that I first
heard about the idea of technical
empathy from one of my mentors Monty
Montgomery and there's something he says
all the time that I think is really
pertinent he says the job of a software
architect although I say broadly whether
you're a software architect or a
software engineer who's been in the
industry for a while he says your job is
to take a development community of a
broad spectrum of Acumen and make them
productive
and that really touches I think a lot on
what we just talked about where if you
have a single voice that's having a
chilling effect then you're going to
struggle to make a development community
of a broad spectrum of Acumen productive
and so you need to find ways to do that
and I think that it to me again is the
measure of what I would call a 10x
engineering they also don't do it alone
right they're able to contribute to
making that development Community
productive even though they have very
different skill sets and you know as
like Robert Martin has been saying for
years there's I think at any given time
half of the engineers in the software
development industry have less than five
years of experience because there's so
many new ones and so the challenge is
not going away the challenge continues
yeah yeah I love that framing so let's
talk a little bit about your company and
how Humana Tech employs these platform
engineering practices and helps
companies to be successful with adopting
them yeah totally so Humanity you know
you were giving this analogy of building
a house right and you don't want to
reinvent everything from the developer
perspective but the same thing is true
from the platform engineer perspective
right you don't want to you know rebuild
the entire stack from scratch right and
what we believe a good platform team
does is they focus on the last mile
optimization right because that's really
is what's going to set your platform
your IDP apart from the rest is a
platform team platform Engineers that
listen right and that really build this
platform you know the tweak that those
last details that and they really make
sense for your own org because otherwise
you might as well have a pass right like
otherwise what's the point of having a
platform team building and IDP right and
I mean again past don't work at the
Enterprise that's why you know sort of
like Heroku was really great at the
beginning and then kind of like flatten
out because they never could figure out
Enterprise right and the Enterprise
everyone is a bit of a special Snowflake
and they need their own platform team
and so the way we think about our
products like human Tech is empowering
this platform teams by giving them an
unopinionated toolbox to go and build
their own opinionated workflows and own
opinionated platforms right and
specifically that toolbox has a core
product which is the plot for marker
straighter and you can think of the
platform orchestrator as a core
configuration and standardization engine
that kind of is at the heart of your
platform layer and then you have drivers
which is an open source library of
connectors that you know let
infrastructure elements communicate with
the chatter and specifically with the
platform orchestrator as well and then
score which is kind of what we touched
on earlier which is this workload
specification and is the sort of at this
point I would say the interface of
reference for developers to interact
with their platform layer and so that's
kind of what we provide and if you think
about it from you know we integrate with
pretty much everything that's out there
like the beauty of this model of the
platform worker Shadow and the drivers
is we integrate with any piece of
infrastructure pretty much and with
anything that you already have right so
we can deploy but if you already have
Argo CD we can let argosity deploy
instead and so the whole point for us is
really around standardization of
configurations both application
infrastructure configurations because as
we said earlier
that's where we see the most pain and
that's what we focus on and then from a
product kind of philosophy perspective
you know our flaws is like integrate and
embrace because again Enterprises
complex right and I think a Roku and
other sort of solutions that try to be
the one size fits all devops all-in-one
kind of you know One-Stop thing that
just doesn't work at the Enterprise and
so we want to be really take a lot of
the pain away but be an easy
plug-and-play solution that can work
with your existing setup
awesome well before we wrap up let's
talk a little bit about the platform con
conference what is it what's your
involvement and why should listeners
attend well I mean they should attend
because Jeff is speaking this year oh
okay well thanks I was not asking for
you to say that but so platform con is
the number one platform engineering
conference we started doing it last year
for the first time and it made a lot of
noise in the industry it got huge
response I think a lot better than what
we ever dreamed of originally we had I
think 7 000 sign ups and about 6 000
attendees just in the day one stream
last year 80 talks you know 20 plus
hours of content so it's amazing it's
virtual it's free so anybody can join
it's a two days long conference it's
going to be on the 9th and 10th of June
this year in platform con 23 and I mean
this year we already see the numbers are
going bananas right so we already
crossed eight thousand sign up so we're
already well above what we did in 22 and
we're still like two three months away
from it and we have amazing sponsors
people like atlassian Docker Google
cloud and we crazy we were talking about
this before jumping on but we had almost
500 talk submissions so we could be
really picky this year we had we picked
130 to 150 is going to be the final
number and so the quality of the
speakers is is really going to be
amazing the quad to the content is going
to be amazing so we're going to have
probably like 40 50 hours of content and
what I'm really excited about is the
format the way you can think about it is
it's completely async right so we
usually have a kickoff where we welcome
everybody that I host both for the
European morning and for the Americas
morning and then you know that's about
20 minutes long and then off you go you
can take your kids to school go to work
whatever and consume content your own
pace and then what we do is we crunch
all the action in a two hours q a on the
platform engineering slack and this is
fantastic because unlike a lot of other
virtual events that you know force you
to use this like weird virtual event
conferences tooling that you know you
kind of like use once and never again
this really leverages two existing
assets of the community the platform
engineering YouTube channel that's where
we publish all the talks as well as
apart from con.com website and the
platform engineering slack where we
already have 11 000 members it's super
active it's really like the Beating
Heart of the community and so there's no
like cold star awkward like people don't
talk like there's already a ton of
action and we basically and platform
conscious becomes like a boost on top of
it right and so what we ask the speakers
to do is hey when the Q a starts the
speakers for that day they start a
threat in the slack basically posting a
link to their YouTube talk with the main
sort of like takeaways and then it's
kind of like hey ask me anything and and
what that does is it starts a frenzy of
threats all over the slack and people
keep engaging and you know you have
cross-pollinations like speakers jumping
on each other's threads is super fun and
also super cool to see last year you
know it's a two days conference and I
thought okay it lasts two days but
actually because the speakers hang out
on the slack anyways and people kept
watching talks in the YouTube the
threats kept going for like 10 or 12
days which was really cool to see so
it's a super fun event it's a bit
different from you know a lot of the
other virtual conferences that people
are used to I think is a lot more fun is
less monotone and we have some of the
best you know platform engineering and
devops people out there speaking so yeah
apart from con.com it's free great so if
listeners want to find out more about
platform engineering they can definitely
go to Humana tax website they can go to
platformcon.com where else might they
find you out on the interwebs yeah
platform engineering.org is another are
great kind of like starting point and
then as for me Luca underscore Cloud
that's where I tweet or platform weekly
that's my newsletter proformweekly.com
great Luca thank you so much for joining
me today on software engineering radio
thank you Jeff this is fun all right
this is Jeff Doolittle for software
engineering radio thanks so much for
listening
thanks for listening to SC radio an
educational program brought to you by
Tripoli software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se.radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn Facebook Twitter or through
our slack Channel at SC radio dot
slack.com you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of SC radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
license 2.5 thanks for listening
[Music]
thank you